Guide to the Civic Club of Allegheny County Records, 1896-1974 AIS.1970.02
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Transit, 1905-1974; IX.
  - Professional Reports Regarding Transit, 1969-1974 (Box 39, Folder 13)
  - Articles and Reports Regarding the Department of Transportation, 1969-1971 (Box 39, Folder 14)
  - "Pittsburgh's Traffic Problem: An immediate Solution with Rail Transit", 1970 (Box 39, Folder 15)
  - Transit Legislation, 1970-1972 (Box 39, Folder 16)
  - Port Authority of Allegheny County Progress Reports, 1970-1972 (Box 39, Folder 17)
  - Reports by the Concerned Tax Payers of Allegheny County Regarding Port Authority, 1970-1973 (Box 39, Folder 18)
  - Reports by Transit Groups, 1970-1971 (Box 39, Folder 19)
  - Cross Sections of Tunnels, 1972 (Box 39, Folder 20)
  - Reports Regarding Transit, 1972-1974 (Box 39, Folder 21)
  - Municipal Workshop on Mass Transit in Allegheny County, 1973 (Box 39, Folder 22)
  - Transportation Task Force, 1973 (Box 39, Folder 23)
  - Port Authority of Allegheny County Seven City Report, undated (Box 39, Folder 24)
- Pollution, 1903-1973; X.
  As an industrial city, Pittsburgh has been plagued by many forms of pollution. From 1908 to 1973, the Civic Club of Allegheny County studied different ways to reduce pollution in the air, water, and streets in order to make the Pittsburgh area a cleaner and healthier place for its residents. Smoke pollution was the top offender in Pittsburgh and the Civic Club spent much of its time working on ways to impede pollution from entering the city's air. Industry was not the only smoke concern, as the Civic Club also led a battle against cigarette smoking on buses in the early 1970s. This expresses their realization that smoke was not only aesthetically displeasing but also unhealthy. Noise pollution, such as car horns, was not as much a health hazard as it was a nuisance. In the early twentieth century the club led a movement to hire an officer whose sole purpose was to stop unnecessary noise Downtown.
  Included in the research and findings of the Civic Club are clippings, correspondence, reports, and pamphlets regarding air, smoke, noise, and water pollution. Other documents include reports by the Allegheny County Health Department, Pollution Control Committee minutes, and local, state and federal environmental and pollution control legislation.
  These files were kept mainly in their original order, by type of pollution, with clippings moved to the beginning of the series and arranged in chronological order. Files within each subject are arranged chronologically.
  - Pollution Clippings, 1956-1973 (Box 39, Folder 25-27)
  - Pollution Control Committee Minutes, 1967-1972 (Box 39, Folder 28-29)
  - National Noise Abatement Council, undated (Box 39, Folder 30)
  - Noise Pollution, 1915-1972 (Box 39, Folder 31-32)
  - Bulletins Regarding Solid Waste, 1969-1972 (Box 39, Folder 33)
  - Solid Waste, 1969-1971 (Box 39, Folder 34)
  - Reports Regarding Water Pollution, 1966-1973 (Box 39, Folder 35)
  - Clippings- Water Pollution, 1967-1971 (Box 39, Folder 36)
  - "Fly Ash Problem-Buried in Deep Mine" by L.R. Love and S.F. Whirl, 1968 (Box 39, Folder 37)
  - Water Pollution Control Training Program Bulletin of Courses, 1968 (Box 39, Folder 38)
  - Review of Pennsylvania Water Pollution Enforcement Program, 1970 (Box 39, Folder 39)
  - Sanitary Complaints, 1903 (Box 39, Folder 40)
  - Sanitary Corps Cleaner Streets, 1917 (Box 39, Folder 41)
  - North Versailles Sanitary Authority, 1969-1972 (Box 39, Folder 42)
  - Reports on Smoke Pollution, 1908, 1913-1915 (Box 39, Folder 43)
  - Report by International Association for the Prevention of Smoke, 1914 (Box 39, Folder 44)
  - Smoke Pollution, 1943-1946 (Box 39, Folder 45)
  - Pennsylvania Department of Health Air Pollution Commission Guidelines, 1960, 1966-1967 (Box 39, Folder 46)
  - Allegheny County Health Department Article on Smoke and Air Pollution Control, 1960, 1967, 1969 (Box 39, Folder 47)
  - United Smoke Council, 1964-1966 (Box 39, Folder 48)
  - Senate Bills Regarding Smoke and Air Pollution, 1967-1969 (Box 39, Folder 49)
  - Pennsylvania Health Department Air Pollution Commission Regulations, 1967-1968 (Box 39, Folder 50)
  - "Guidelines for Developing Air Quality Standards and Air Quality Criteria for Sulfur Oxides and Particulate Matter", 1969 (Box 39, Folder 51)
  - "Economic Evaluation of Sulfur Dioxide Air Pollution Incident Control", 1969 (Box 39, Folder 52)
  - Pennsylvania Department of Health Air Pollution Commission Regulations, 1969 (Box 39, Folder 53)
  - Presentation for Public Hearing on Pennsylvania Proposed Ambient Air Quality Standards, 1969 (Box 39, Folder 54)
  - Pennsylvania Department of Health Air Quality Standards, 1969 (Box 39, Folder 55)
  - Allegheny County Health Department Article on Air Pollution Control, 1969- 1970 (Box 40, Folder 1)
  - Proposed Implementation Plan for Pittsburgh Air Quality Control Region, 1970 (Box 40, Folder 2)
  - Hines Smog Retarder, 1970-1973 (Box 40, Folder 3)
  - Smoking on Buses, 1971-1972 (Box 40, Folder 4)
  - Allegheny County Bureau of Air Pollution Control Clean Air Monitor, 1973 (Box 40, Folder 5)
  - Pittsburgh Smoke Control, undated (Box 40, Folder 6)
  - Reports and Minutes from Area Industrial Problems Committee, 1966 (Box 40, Folder 7)
  - Reports from Area Industrial Problems Committee, 1967 (Box 40, Folder 8)
  - Reports from Allegheny County Health Department, 1966, 1970 (Box 40, Folder 09-10)
  - Miscellaneous Reports and Pamphlets Regarding Pollution, undated (Box 40, Folder 11)
  - "Report Concerning Intercepting Sewerage Sewage Treatment and Disposal", 1939 (Box 40, Folder 12)
  - Federal Pollution Standards, 1966-1969 (Box 40, Folder 13)
  - "Municipal Waste Facilities in the United States", 1968 (Box 40, Folder 14)
  - Reports and Pamphlets Regarding Pollution, 1969-1970 (Box 40, Folder 15-17)
  - Community Affairs Support Bulletin, 1969-1970 (Box 40, Folder 18)
  - Documents Regarding Pollution Control Legislation, 1969-1970 (Box 40, Folder 19)
  - Environmental Law Volume 1 Number 1, 1970 (Box 40, Folder 20)
  - Articles Regarding Pollution, 1970-1971 (Box 40, Folder 21)
  - Proposed Tax Incentives for Pollution Control, 1970-1971 (Box 40, Folder 22)
  - Environmental Protection Agency Newsletters, 1971-1973 (Box 40, Folder 23)
  - Articles Regarding Energy, 1972-1973 (Box 40, Folder 24)
- Club Finances, 1895-1974; XI.
  The finances of the Civic Club were never strong and often relied upon contributions from members to settle debts. Over time, various fund raisers did not make up for the increasing indebtedness and the club took out several bank loans. Unfortunately, these only contributed to the financial problems of the Civic Club and led to its dissolution in 1974.
  Included are Treasurer Reports, office leases, tax exemption documents, club assets, and bank statements. Also present are files of correspondence concerning the club's fragile financial status and dissolution. Early club finance records can be found with the Board of Directors minutes in Series II.
  - Petty Cash Books, 1895-1897 (Box 40, Folder 25)
  - Treasurer's Statements, 1912-1918, 1929 (Box 40, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence Regarding the Borrowing of Funds, 1926-1931 (Box 40, Folder 27)
  - Flower Market Fund Raiser, 1928-1929 (Box 40, Folder 28)
  - Contributions to Civic Club, 1933, 1966-1972 (Box 40, Folder 29)
  - Income and Expense Reports, 1946-1955, 1970-1973 (Box 40, Folder 30)
  - Civic Club Federal Income Tax Exemption, 1948-1949, 1970-1972 (Box 40, Folder 31)
  - Office Leases and Correspondence, 1954-1957 (Box 40, Folder 32)
  - Bank Statement and Financial Papers, 1965-1971 (Box 40, Folder 33)
  - Liberty Amendment Committee Balance Book, 1965-1971 (Box 40, Folder 34)
  - Correspondence and Leases with William Penn Hotel, 1966-1971 (Box 40, Folder 35)
  - Civic Club Bank Loans and Debt, 1966-1974 (Box 40, Folder 36)
  - Treasurer Reports, 1966-1974 (Box 40, Folder 37)
  - Correspondence- Treasurer, 1966-1969, 1973 (Box 40, Folder 38)
  - Correspondence- Club Finances, 1966-1973 (Box 40, Folder 39-40)
  - Membership Dues, 1967-1969 (Box 40, Folder 41)
  - Charitable Exemption of Sales Tax, 1967-1970 (Box 40, Folder 42)
  - Correspondence- Chatham Communications, 1970-1971 (Box 40, Folder 43)
  - Civic Club Assets, 1970-1972 (Box 40, Folder 44)
  - Civic Club Balance Sheets, 1973 (Box 40, Folder 45)
  - Financial Problems, 1973 (Box 40, Folder 46)
  - Drawings and Contract for New Office Furniture, 1973 (Box 40, Folder 47)
  - Correspondence and Leases with Frick Building, 1973-1974 (Box 40, Folder 48)
  - "Major Firms in the Pittsburgh Metro Area", 1974 (Box 40, Folder 49)
  - Civic Club Dissolution and Trustee List, 1974-1975 (Box 40, Folder 50)
  - Civic Club Bank Account Closure, 1974-1975 (Box 40, Folder 51)
- Voters' Directory, 1930-1974; XII.
  The Voters' Directory was started in 1930 by the Civic Club of Allegheny County. Its main objective was to educate voters in a nonpartisan manner about candidates and issues before they went to the polls. At first the Directories were free of charge, but due to their overwhelming popularity the printing costs were beginning to pull the club deeper into debt; therefore, a small charge was added in order for the continuation of this public service. Voters' Directory pamphlets could be found in bulk at local businesses and even in local schools where, in some cases, the students were instructed on their use during Civics class. These lessons gave students the opportunity to study the responsibilities of voters firsthand before they were of voting age. The Directories themselves are a rich source of biographical information for candidates who ran for local, state and national positions between 1930 and 1974. Biographical information of such prominent candidates as Anne X. Alpern, K. Leroy Irvis, Henry John Heinz III, and Jo Ann Evans Gardner, among others, can be found in the directories in this series.
  Included in these records are a Voters' Directory copyright certificate, correspondence concerning pamphlet production and delivery, clippings, committee minutes, and Voters' Directory pamphlets. A photo of F.E. Schuchman and George W. Shankey, Jr. tying up stacks of Directories is also present.
  - Voters' Directory History, undated (Box 40, Folder 52)
  - Voters' Directories, 1930-1948 (Box 40, Folder 53-71)
  - Voters' Directories, 1949-1974 (Box 41, Folder 01-26)
  - Legislative Directories, 1927-1952 (Box 41, Folder 27)
  - Clippings- Voters' Directory, 1928-1958 (Box 41, Folder 28-31)
  - Voter Information, 1935-1973 (Box 41, Folder 32)
  - Copyright Certificate for Voters' Directory, 1941 (Box 41, Folder 33)
  - Voters' Directory Production and Delivery, 1947, 1968-1974 (Box 41, Folder 34)
  - Voters' Directory Committee Minutes and Lists, 1952-1972 (Box 41, Folder 35)
  - Suggestion that Schools Teach Voters' Directory Use, 1953 (Box 41, Folder 36)
  - Letters of Appreciation for Voters' Directory, 1966-1972 (Box 41, Folder 37)
  - Correspondence and Directories from League of Women Voters, 1966, 1972 (Box 41, Folder 38)
  - Pennsylvania Voters' Directories, 1966, 1972 (Box 41, Folder 39)
  - Voters' Directory Solicitation Form Letters, 1966-1974 (Box 41, Folder 40)
  - Voters' Directory Letters to Candidates, 1967-1974 (Box 41, Folder 41)
  - Correspondence- Voters' Directory Donors and Sales, 1967-1973 (Box 41, Folder 42)
  - Voter Education Week, 1968-1972 (Box 41, Folder 43)
  - Other Cities' Voters' Directories, 1968-1973 (Box 41, Folder 44)
  - Photo of Shankey and Schuchman with Directories, ca.1974 (Box 41, Folder 45)
- George W. Shankey, Jr., 1966-1974; XIII.
  George W. Shankey, Jr. was born in 1908 in Avalon, Pennsylvania. He served as ¬¬¬¬¬¬ Executive Vice President of the Civic Club during its final few years. His most notable contribution to the club was writing and presenting reports to members of the local and state government on various subjects such as city, county, and school budgets, taxation, transportation, and county government structure, thus assuring that the Civic Club's opinions were heard. Shankey ran for the positions of County Commissioner in 1971 and United States Senator in 1974, both under the Constitutional Party of Allegheny County. While running for Commissioner, he and another Constitutional Party candidate, John McManus, became involved in the 1971 court case known as Shankey-McManus v. WABCO (Westinghouse Air Brake Company). They accused a WABCO employee of sending political material promoting Hunt and Stokes, two of their opponents, through the mail using WABCO's postage meter. The utilization of corporate resources for political gain was in violation of the election code and an investigation ensued. In response, Shankey was accused of obtaining technical data from WABCO, thus breaking the same rule; however, it was determined that this material was received in 1969 for Civic Club research and was well before he had chosen to run for office.
  Included are copies of several presentations, correspondence about the WABCO case, transcripts of campaign speeches, a photo and campaign pamphlets. A presentation by Shankey on the subject of Home Rule can be found in Series V.
  - Correspondence and Photo of George W. Shankey, Jr., 1966-1973 (Box 41, Folder 46)
  - Reports on Local and County Government by George W. Shankey, Jr., 1967, 1971 (Box 41, Folder 47)
  - Presentation on City Budget by George W. Shankey, Jr., 1968-1972 (Box 41, Folder 48)
  - Presentation on Urban Problems by George W. Shankey, Jr., 1969 (Box 41, Folder 49)
  - Presentations on Transportation by George W. Shankey, Jr., 1969-1974 (Box 41, Folder 50)
  - Presentations on Taxation by George W. Shankey, Jr. and J.H. Neely, 1969-1971 (Box 41, Folder 51)
  - Constitutional Party of Allegheny County- Shankey and McManus for County Commissioner, 1971 (Box 41, Folder 52-53)
  - Shankey-McManus v. WABCO, 1971 (Box 41, Folder 54)
  - Presentation to County Commissioners by George W. Shankey, Jr., 1972 (Box 41, Folder 55)
  - Review of School Budget and Dr. Kishkuna's Austerity Program by George W. Shankey, Jr., 1971-1972 (Box 41, Folder 56)
  - Presentation to City Government Study Commission by George W. Shankey, Jr., 1973 (Box 41, Folder 57)
  - Testimony for Concerned Taxpayers of Allegheny County to Senate Committee on Agriculture by George W. Shankey, Jr., 1973 (Box 41, Folder 58)
  - Presentation on City Council Structure by George W. Shankey, Jr., 1974 (Box 41, Folder 59)
  - Constitutional Party of Allegheny County- George W. Shankey, Jr. for U.S. Senator, 1974 (Box 41, Folder 60)
- Film and Audio Tape, 1927-1967; XIV.
  This series includes a 16 millimeter film concerning the Civic Club Flower Market and another of an IDE interview. Several quarter inch audio tapes are present and cover such topics as the Stadium Authority, the Golden Triangle, and a George W. Shankey, Jr. press conference concerning local government, among others.
  - Flower Market, 1927 (Box 42, Reel 1)
  - Ide Interview, undated (Box 42, Reel 2)
  - Allegheny Roundtable, April 26, 1967 (Box 42, Reel 3)
  - "The Lure of Superiority" Address by Dr. Samuel N. Stevens at a Junior Achievement Banquet, May 14, 1954 (Box 42, Reel 4)
  - Stadium Authority Press Conference, September, 1966 (Box 42, Reel 5)
  - George W. Shankey, Jr. News Conference on Local Government, undated (Box 42, Reel 6)
  - Golden Triangle Board of Public Works Meeting, Speaker Isabelle Allias, September 2, 1965 (Box 42, Reel 7)
  - WQED Public Affairs Program "Let's Talk It Over" Hosted by Civic Club Member Steelgow Concerning Fiscal Policies, undated (Box 42, Reel 8)